<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
Copyright 2006-2007, by the California Institute of Technology.
ALL RIGHTS RESERVED. United States Government Sponsorship acknowledged.
Any commercial use must be negotiated with the Office of Technology Transfer
at the California Institute of Technology.

This software is subject to U. S. export control laws and regulations
(22 C.F.R. 120-130 and 15 C.F.R. 730-774). To the extent that the software
is subject to U.S. export control laws and regulations, the recipient has
the responsibility to obtain export licenses or other export authority as
may be required before exporting such information to foreign countries or
providing access to foreign nationals.

$Id$
-->

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Installation</title>
    <author email="Michael.Cayanan@jpl.nasa.gov">Michael Cayanan</author>
    <author email="Sean.Hardman@jpl.nasa.gov">Sean Hardman</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Installing the Tools">
      <p>This section describes how to install the tools contained in the <i>product-tools</i> package. The following topics can be found in this section:
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li><a href="#System Requirements">System Requirements</a></li>
        <li><a href="#Unpacking the Tools Package">Unpacking the Tools Package</a></li>
        <li><a href="#Modifying Shell Scripts">Modifying Shell Scripts</a></li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section name="System Requirements">
      <subsection name="Java Requirement">
        <p>The tools contained in the <i>product-tools</i> package were developed using Java and will run on any platform with a supported Java Runtime Environment (JRE). The tools were specifically developed under Sun Java version 1.4, so the tool will execute correctly under versions 1.4 or 1.5.
        </p>

        <p>Since the tools are developed using Sun's Java, this is the preferred Java environment for operation. The Sun Java package can be obtained from the <a href="http://java.sun.com/" target="_blank"> Sun Java</a> web site. Other Java environments are relatively compatible with Sun's Java. Testing has been performed with GNU's Java environment. The result is that release 4.1.1 at a minimum is required for nominal operations.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Data Dictionary Requirement">
        <p>With this release of VTool, the requirement of using the provided PDS data dictionary is no longer necessary. Through the efforts of many, the anomalies found in past versions of the data dictionary have been corrected in release <i>1r64</i>. So, this release or later of the data dictionary is required for VTool. The latest version of the PDS data dictionary can be retrieved from the <a href="http://pds.nasa.gov/tools/data_dictionary_lookup.cfm" target="_blank">PDS Data Dictionary Lookup</a> web page.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Unpacking the Tools Package">
      <p>Download the <i>product-tools</i> package from the Engineering Node web site as specified in the Release Description Document (RDD). The binary distribution is available in identical zip or tar/gzip packages. Unpack the selected file with one of the following commands (where X.X.X is the current version):
      </p>

      <source>
[node: ~] unzip product-tools-X.X.X.zip
or
[node: ~] tar -xzvf product-tools-X.X.X.tar.gz
      </source>

      <p><b>Note:</b> Depending on the platform, the native version of <i>tar</i> may produce an error when attempting to unpack the distribution file because many of the file paths are greater than 100 characters. If available, the GNU version of tar will resolve this problem. If that is not available or cannot be installed, the zipped package will work just fine in a UNIX environment.
      </p>

      <p>The above commands result in the creation of the <i>product-tools-X.X.X</i> directory with the following directory structure:
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li><b>LICENSE.txt</b>
          <p>The copyright notice from the California Institute of Technology detailing the restrictions regarding the use and distribution of this software.
          </p>
        </li>
        <li><b>bin/</b>
            <p>This directory contains the executable jar file containing the Validation Tool software.
          </p>
        </li>
        <li><b>docs/</b>
          <p>This document directory contains a local web site with the Product Tools Guide, javadoc, unit test results and other configuration management related information. Just point your favorite browser to the <i>index.html</i> file in this directory.
          </p>
        </li>
        <li><b>lib/</b>
          <p>This directory contains the dependent jar files for the tool along with the jar file (product-tools-X.X.X.jar) containing the Validation Tool software.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Modifying Shell Scripts">
      <p>A batch file, <i>VTool.bat</i>, and shell script, <i>VTool</i>, is included in the product-tools package to provide an easy way of running the Validation Tool without having to setup the CLASSPATH environment variable as documented in the <a href="../user/index.html" target="_blank">Tool Setup</a> section or having to call the java command each time (java gov.nasa.pds.tools.VTool ...).
      </p>
      
      <p>In both the batch file and shell script, there is a variable called <i>jarpath</i> that needs to be modified before the scripts can be executed. The variable needs to be set to the correct location of the executable product tools jar file.
      </p>
      
      <p>The following demonstrates the jarpath being set to the product-tools jar file location. The example contains <i>X.X.X</i>, which represents the current version of the <i>product-tools</i> package.
      </p>
      
      <p>Note: The example has been broken into multiple lines for readability.
      </p>
      <source>
set jarpath = \
"/home/user/product-tools-X.X.X/bin/product-tools-X.X.X-app.jar"
      </source>      
    </section>
    
  </body>
</document>
