<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
Copyright 2007-2009, by the California Institute of Technology.
ALL RIGHTS RESERVED. United States Government Sponsorship acknowledged.
Any commercial use must be negotiated with the Office of Technology Transfer
at the California Institute of Technology.

This software is subject to U. S. export control laws and regulations
(22 C.F.R. 120-130 and 15 C.F.R. 730-774). To the extent that the software
is subject to U.S. export control laws and regulations, the recipient has
the responsibility to obtain export licenses or other export authority as
may be required before exporting such information to foreign countries or
providing access to foreign nationals.

$Id$
-->

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Release Notes</title>
    <author email="Sean.Hardman@jpl.nasa.gov">Sean Hardman</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Release Notes">
      <p>The purpose of this section is to provide a description of a Product Tools release including any impact that the new or modified capabilities will have on the Discipline Nodes or the PDS user community. A somewhat itemized list of changes for each release can be found on the <a href="../changes-report.html">Release Changes</a> page. If viewing this document in PDF form, see the appendix for details.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Release 2.0.0">
      <p>This release of the Product Tools software incorporates the Phase II capability supporting validation of catalog files.
      </p>

      <p>The major change for this release is the addition of support for validating catalog files, either standalone or as a set within a CATALOG directory. Modifications to support this capability included a general change with regard to how pointers are handled as well as relaxing some of the PDS Label constraints where catalog files do not conform to those constraints. The result is that catalog files are now validated correctly and the spurious messages that were previously produced have been eliminated.
      </p>

      <p>The other change in this release involved correct validation of quoted date/time strings. Date/time strings may not be quoted when associated with an element that is defined with one of the DATE data types.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

