<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
Copyright 2006-2007, by the California Institute of Technology.
ALL RIGHTS RESERVED. United States Government Sponsorship acknowledged.
Any commercial use must be negotiated with the Office of Technology Transfer
at the California Institute of Technology.

This software is subject to U. S. export control laws and regulations
(22 C.F.R. 120-130 and 15 C.F.R. 730-774). To the extent that the software
is subject to U.S. export control laws and regulations, the recipient has
the responsibility to obtain export licenses or other export authority as
may be required before exporting such information to foreign countries or
providing access to foreign nationals.

$Id$
-->

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Release Changes</title>
    <author email="Sean.Hardman@jpl.nasa.gov">Sean Hardman</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <release version="1.1.1" date="2007-11-08" description="This is a maintenance release of the Product Tools software to support release 0.3.0 of the Label Template Design Tool.">
      <action dev="mcayanan" type="add">
        Added handler classes for the tools logging capability.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.1.0" date="2007-09-28" description="This is a maintenance release of the Product Tools software including fixes and changes requested by the early adopters of the software.">
      <action dev="shardman" type="remove">
        The Validation Tool application has been split out from the <i>product-tools</i> project in order to provide more specific documentation and to turn the <i>product-tools</i> project into a library of classes that can be included by other projects. The following files or directories were moved:
        <ul>
          <li>src/java/gov/nasa/pds/tools/VTool.java</li>
          <li>src/java/gov/nasa/pds/tools/flags/VToolFlags.java</li>
          <li>src/java/gov/nasa/pds/tools/config/</li>
          <li>src/java/gov/nasa/pds/tools/status/</li>
          <li>src/resources/scripts/</li>
          <li>xdocs/install/</li>
          <li>xdocs/user/</li>
        </ul>
      </action>
      <action dev="pramirez" type="add">
        Added support for aliases in the dictionary. They are now handled more uniformly and there is an explicit class for dealing with them.
      </action>
      <action dev="pramirez" type="add">
        Capability to write a dictionary to a file is now supported using the DictionaryWriter class.
      </action>
      <action dev="pramirez" type="add">
        Label class now persists numbers of errors and warnings found during validation. This was added to support some of the return value information that will now be provided.
      </action>
      <action dev="shardman" type="add">
        Added README files to be included with the binary and source distribution packages. The binary version points the user to the documentation provided with the package. The source version informs the user that they are on their own with regard to building the source in their own environment.
      </action>
      <action dev="shardman" type="add">
        Added the somewhat human-readable representation of the grammer utilized to parse PDS labels to the Development section of the documentation. This is currently a manual process that is documented in the DEPLOY.txt file, which can be found in the root directory of this project.
      </action>
      <action dev="pramirez" type="update">
        Added support for namespaces in identifiers. There is now a class that handles parsing out of the namespace in an identifier. This was being done in multiple places in the code before so was a way to clean things up.
      </action>
      <action dev="pramirez" type="update">
        Updated fields in definitions to support all that was found in the dictionary. There were some missing fields before now everything read in is preserved.
      </action>
      <action dev="pramirez" type="fix">
        Times can no longer reside on the right hand side of an attribute statement without being proceeded by a date. This was being allowed by the grammar but is not part of the standard.
      </action>
      <action dev="pramirez" type="fix">
        The map of definitions returned from the dictionary class contained redundant definitions and used a naming convention that was not explicitly called out. This was cleaned up and now the map returns only a single copy of the definitions. In additioned the weird naming convention has been tossed.
      </action>
      <action dev="pramirez" type="fix">
        Aliases in the dictionary were not be correctly read in or handled all the time. There was some errant information found in the dictionary. This has been removed and fixed.
      </action>
      <action dev="pramirez" type="fix">
        Validation layer now ensures that there is not duplicate attribute identifiers within the same block. For instance, will report an error when multiple "TARGET_NAME"s are found.
      </action>
      <action dev="pramirez" type="fix">
        GROUP definitions in the data dictionary can now be specified as a SPECIFIC_OBJECT_DEFINITION as well as a GENERIC_OBJECT_DEFINITION.
      </action>
      <action dev="pramirez" type="fix">
        Messages regarding unknown unit values will now have a severity of WARNING instead of ERROR.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.0.0" date="2007-05-04" description="This release of the Product Tools software, including the Validation Tool, represents the operational release for the Phase I targeted capabilities.">         
      <action dev="pramirez" type="add">
        Added support for validation of label fragments.
      </action>      
      
      <action dev="mcayanan" type="add">
        Added the capability to return an appropriate exit status value based on validation results or tool application failure.
      </action>      
      
      <action dev="mcayanan" type="add">
        Created batch and shell scripts for simpler execution of VTool.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="mcayanan" type="add">
        Added the capability for targets to be specified implicitly.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="mcayanan" type="add">
        Added -f or --force flag option to perform standalone label fragment validation.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="pramirez" type="update">
        Validation of units is now performed against the master list of unit values. This comparison is case sensitive.
      </action>

      <action dev="pramirez" type="update">
        File names referenced by pointers may be in any case and still be discoverable by the tool. File names in mixed case will generate a warning message.
      </action>

      <action dev="pramirez" type="update">
        Cleaned up reporting including replacing SEVERE with ERROR in all instances and properly representing fragment messages when they are included in a label validation.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="mcayanan" type="update">
        Implemented new log file behavior to allow logs to be written to memory. This allows generation of reports without the need of explicitly specifying the log file flag option. 
      </action>

      <action dev="mcayanan" type="update">
        Changed the log file flag (-l or --log) option to optionally allow a file specification. See <i>Use and Operation</i> guide for log generation details.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="mcayanan" type="update">
        Added time and date of tool execution in final reports.
      </action>
           
      <action dev="mcayanan" type="update">
        Enhanced user guide with more details regarding command-line flag options, report examples, etc.
      </action>      
           
      <action dev="mcayanan" type="fix">
        Fixed support for UNC pathnames.
      </action>

      <action dev="mcayanan" type="fix">
        Fixed the minimal report stylesheet to work correctly on the Linux platform.
      </action>
    </release>
    
    <release version="0.4.0" date="2007-02-01" description="Binary release for the beta test phase.">
      <action dev="pramirez" type="add">
        Added the following capabilities related to semantic validation:
        <ul>
          <li>White space stripping for element value comparison.</li>
          <li>Support for element and object aliases.</li>
          <li>Verifying the existence of referenced data objects and files.</li>
        </ul>
      </action>

      <action dev="pramirez" type="add">
        Implemented reporting including generation of an XML formatted log file which can then be transformed via XSLT stylesheeets into the specified human-readable report formats.
      </action>

      <action dev="mcayanan" type="add">
        Implemented progress reporting, which prints to standard error. This feature will report the directory being validated and then represent each file being validated with an asterisk instead of the actual file name.
      </action>

      <action dev="shardman" type="add">
        Added documentation for Installation and a template for Develoment along with the capability to generate a PDF of the newly named Product Tools Guide.
      </action>

      <action dev="mcayanan" type="update">
        Added and/or modified the following command-line options:
        
        <table>
          <tr><td>-a</td><td>Enable aliasing</td></tr>
          <tr><td>-I</td><td>Specify paths to look for files referenced by pointer statements in a label</td></tr>
          <tr><td>-l</td><td>Specify a file name for the machine-readable log</td></tr>
          <tr><td>-p</td><td>Enable progress reporting</td></tr>
          <tr><td>-r</td><td>Specify a file name for the human-readable report</td></tr>
          <tr><td>-s</td><td>Specify a format for the human-readable report</td></tr>
          <tr><td>-v</td><td>Specify the severity level and above to include in the human-reable report</td></tr>
        </table>
      </action>

      <action dev="mcayanan" type="update">
        Changed the "p" (patterns) flag to an "e" (regexp) flag. Also changed the "l" (local) flag to an "L" flag.
      </action>

      <action dev="mcayanan" type="update">
        Updated VTool to validate files in a directory first before moving on to its sub-directories. Before, validation of files in a directory were interleaved with validation of files in its sub-directories.
      </action>

      <action dev="shardman" type="update">
        Added a <i>Common Errors</i> section to the User Guide as well as clarifying some aspects of setting the <i>CLASSPATH</i> environment variable in the <i>Setup</i> section.
      </action>

      <action dev="pramirez" type="fix">
        Corrected a problem where the tool was not completing syntactic validation on a label.
      </action>

      <action dev="mcayanan" type="fix">
        Fixed to properly handle URLs (for targets, dictionaries, Includes).
      </action>
    </release>
    
    <release version="0.3.0" date="2006-09-12" description="Binary release for the second phase of alpha testing.">
      <action dev="mcayanan" type="add">
        Added a user guide for VTool.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="mcayanan" type="add">
        Added the following command-line options:
          <table>
            <tr><td>-o</td><td>Write the validation results to a file</td></tr>
            <tr><td>-p</td><td>Specify files/file patterns to include in validation</td></tr>
            <tr><td>-X</td><td>Specify files/file patterns to exclude in validation</td></tr>
            <tr><td>-c</td><td>Specify a configuration file to set default behaviors</td></tr>
            <tr><td>-F</td><td>Do not follow STRUCTURE pointers</td></tr>
          </table>
      </action>
      
      <action dev="pramirez" type="add">
        Pointers are now followed. This feature can be turned on and off. This will allow arbitrary length nesting of pointers. Object and group statements should not begin and end in different files. Their contents may be in separate files but the open and close should be contained within the same file. This will allow the label to be valid even when semantic validation is done.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="pramirez" type="add">
        Added support for PDS_VERSION_ID. Now files that don't have this in the first line will be skipped and logged as a warning if passed to the parser.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="pramirez" type="add">
        Added support for SFDUs. Now the SFDUs will be logged and then skipped. This has not added validation of SFDUs.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="mcayanan" type="update">
        Changed the "f" (file) flag to a "t" (target) flag.
      </action> 
      
      <action dev="pramirez" type="update">
        Dates are now checked to ensure that they are not only properly formed but are actual valid dates. One can now get a Date
        object through the API for convenience.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="pramirez" type="update">
        More logging information about file being parsed and dictionaries being used.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="mcayanan" type="fix">
        Fixed multiple dictionary support.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="pramirez" type="fix">
        Properly handle the 'Z' at the end of the date when attempting to create an actual Date object.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="pramirez" type="fix">
        Allow group statements to be within object statements.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="pramirez" type="fix">
        Allow for objects and groups with the same name to appear at the same level within a label or fragment. This required changes to method signatures on the Label class.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="pramirez" type="fix">
        Fixed convenience methods on Label class. This would have only caused a problem if people called the tool directly.
      </action>
      
      <action dev="pramirez" type="fix">
        PSDD will now be adhered to properly as an optional element. This essentially allows any element definition to appear within an object or group statement without generating an error.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.2.0" date="2006-08-01" description="Binary release for the first phase of alpha testing.">
      <action dev="pramirez" type="update" due-to="Mark Rose" due-to-email="mrose@email.arc.nasa.gov">
        A major overhaul to how the grammar was implemented using Antlr was performed as a result of comments from the Code Walk-through.
      </action>
      <action dev="pramirez" type="add">
        This release supports validation against the PDS Data Dictionary.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.1.0" date="2006-06-16" description="Source release for the Code Walk-through.">
      <action dev="pramirez" type="add">
        This release supports syntactic and semantic validation of a single PDS label.
      </action>
    </release>
  </body>
</document>
