<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
Copyright 2006-2007, by the California Institute of Technology.
ALL RIGHTS RESERVED. United States Government Sponsorship acknowledged.
Any commercial use must be negotiated with the Office of Technology Transfer
at the California Institute of Technology.

This software is subject to U. S. export control laws and regulations
(22 C.F.R. 120-130 and 15 C.F.R. 730-774). To the extent that the software
is subject to U.S. export control laws and regulations, the recipient has
the responsibility to obtain export licenses or other export authority as
may be required before exporting such information to foreign countries or
providing access to foreign nationals.

$Id$
-->

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Development</title>
    <author email="Paul.Ramirez@jpl.nasa.gov">Paul Ramirez</author>
    <author email="Sean.Hardman@jpl.nasa.gov">Sean Hardman</author>
    <author email="Michael.Cayanan@jpl.nasa.gov">Michael Cayanan</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Developing Tools">
       <p>This section describes how a user can utilize the underlying Application Program Interface (API) of the <i>product-tools</i> package to develop their own tool. This section also covers how to interpret the exit status values returned by the tool if the user calls the <i>VTool</i> class from a script.
       </p>
       
       <subsection name="API Entry Points">
         <p>We have not had a chance to document the entry points into the API as of the current release. The best source for this information currently is to view the <i>VTool.java</i> file from the source package.
         </p>
       </subsection>

       <subsection name="Exit Status Values">
         <p>The Validation Tool returns an exit status based on the PDS validation results or if an application failure has occurred. This section details what exit status values to expect when the tool is validating a single data product label and when it is validating multiple data product labels in a single run.
         </p>
         
         <p><b>Validation Of A Single Data Product</b></p>
         
         <p>The following table shows what exit values can be returned when the tool validates just one data product label in a single run:
         </p>
         
         <table>
           <tr><th nowrap="nowrap">Exit Status Value</th><th>Meaning</th></tr>
           <tr><td><center>0</center></td><td>The data product label has passed the PDS validation step.</td></tr>
           <tr><td><center>1</center></td><td>The data product label has failed or skipped the PDS validation step.</td></tr>
           <tr><td><center>-1</center></td><td>A tool application error has occurred (invalid command-line option, file cannot be read, etc.)</td></tr>
         </table>
         
         <p><b>Validation Of Multiple Data Products</b></p>
         
         <p>The following table shows what exit values can be returned when the tool validates multiple data product labels in a single run:
         </p>
         
         <table>
           <tr><th nowrap="nowrap">Exit Status Value</th><th>Meaning</th></tr>
           <tr><td><center>0</center></td><td>One of the following has occurred:
                                            <ul>
                                              <li>All data product labels have passed the PDS validation step.</li>
                                              <li>Data product labels have passed and skipped the PDS validation step.</li>
                                            </ul>
                                          </td></tr>
           <tr><td><center>1</center></td><td>One of the following has occurred:
                                            <ul>
                                              <li>One or more of the data product labels has failed the PDS validation step.</li>
                                              <li>All data product labels have skipped the validation step.</li>
                                            </ul>
                                          </td></tr>
           <tr><td><center>-1</center></td><td>A tool application error has occurred (invalid command-line option, file cannot be read, etc.)</td></tr>
         </table>         
       </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
